War ravaging the East since 1937 and
Japan's invasion of China
reached Europe on the 1st of September
1939 with Germany's invasion of Poland.
It became global on the 7th of December
1941 when Japanese [music] aircraft
attacked the American naval base at
Pearl Harbor.
It touched every continent
and lasted for six years.
It ended with a new weapon for a new
age.
This is the [music] history of the
greatest of all man-made events.
These men are part of that history. They
are eyewitnesses to the triumphs and
tragedies of the war wherever it was
fought.
Their testimony is part of the story of
how our world was made
by those who could pay
and those who [music] could no longer
meet
the [music] price of empire.
In the last episode of the price of
empire, the allies opened the second
front in Europe. Now they will break out
of the Normandy beach head and begin
their drive on the Rine.
The Red Army will launch its summer
offensive, Operation Bration, the start
of its drive on Berlin.
In the east, the invasion of the
Philippines will bring the Allies a step
closer to Japan's home islands.
Everywhere, [music]
the Axis nations will be fighting
opponents whose terms are unconditional
surrender.
The Japanese foreign minister Shigamitsu
may have spoken for the axis when he
said, "Hell is on us.
In November 1942, Hitler had given the
German people their first hint that the
fortunes of war would be turned their
way by Veel Tugvan
revenge weapons.
half an oint [music] the V1
and spy the V2.
They caused more than 30,000 casualties,
but wonder weapons were not to influence
the outcome of the war. They were too
late and offered too little return for
an enormous investment that might have
been better placed. The armies that
invaded Normandy were fully mechanized.
The Vmar still relied on 1 and a4
million horses.
In 1944, a very different weapon might
have altered the course of the conflict,
but it misfired.
German army officers have revolted
against Hitler, but they failed in the
attempt to blow him up.
>> There had been at least 10 attempts on
Hitler's life during his rise to power
and almost 20 more since he had become
furer.
A couple had got close, most had not.
But Operation Valkyrie was different. It
was not the work of the resistance of
communists or of Cranks. It was a plot
hatched within and to be executed by the
military. Some of the most senior and
most aristocratic men in the military
who paid with their lives for a
mismanaged [music] plot.
What more than anything else had turned
them against Hitler was Stalingrad,
evidence to them that the war was being
ineptly [music]
run.
With Hitler both physically and [music]
psychologically damaged by the near
escape at the Vulchansa, his East
Prussian headquarters, Germany's future
[music] was in shaky hands when on the
Eastern front in Western Europe and in
Italy, [music]
a firm hand was desperately needed.
In Italy, a campaign that had taken
months to grind its way north had at
last got beyond Rome and faced the next
German defensive barrier, the Gothic
line,
where things did not get any easier.
Seasoned Allied units were withdrawn to
prepare for the planned invasion of
southern France
and were replaced by 25,000 Brazilian
[music] troops. Brazil having declared
war on the Axis in August of 42 and by
the US 92nd Division,
the only Africanamean division to see
active service in Europe, the Buffalo
Division.
Before turning to the fortunes of the
Italian campaign, we must look at the
campaign that had taken the best of the
American and free French troops away
from Italy.
Operation Dragoon.
Dragoon was a clear demonstration of
which ally was the senior partner.
Churchill did not agree with it. Neither
did his service chiefs. But Roosevelt
wanted it and so did his top brass. Most
of all,
they wanted Marseilles [music] as a port
that could land supplies for the
invading army.
Churchill's concern was not military. It
was political. To him, [music] weakening
the Italian campaign, which promised to
drive up into central Europe, was
tantamount [music] to abandoning Eastern
Germany, Czechoslovakia, Poland, even
the Balkans, to the advancing [music]
Soviet army, and so to the Soviet Union.
Stalin predictably approved Roosevelt's
decision, but Churchill, a published
historian, knew his history.
Officials Zarist war aims in 1914 had
envisaged a Russo-German border on the
line Odin Misa and is what Soviet Russia
was to achieve in 1945.
Operation Dragoon delayed until mid
August for want of landing craft was
irrelevant to the geopolitical reality.
The opposition encountered in the south
was very swiftly overcome by the
airborne troops and by the seaborn
forces who went into land under cover of
a naval bombardment.
And this is it. The opening of the
fourth front. The third piercing thrust
at Nazi held France.
Within a couple of days, the Allies were
breaking out of their Cop Dazura beach
heads as German forces began to
withdraw.
In a campaign of barely four weeks,
Dragoon evicted German forces, but was
unable to keep pace with their retreat.
Just over 2,000 Allied and 7,000 German
lives were lost in a campaign that came
too late to make a significant
difference to the support and supply of
events in Normandy.
Churchill's fears were to be justified.
The Allied failure [music] to beat the
Russians to or at least meet the
Russians in Central Europe shaped world
politics for half a century. It was,
according to American General Mark
Clark, [music] the outstanding political
mistake of the war.
The speed with which the American 7th
Army moved following its landings in the
south of France was not matched by Mark
Clark's Fifth Army.
On Italy's Adriatic coast, the British
8th Army faced the Gothic line where it
turned at a right angle to follow the
[music] Aenine Mountain chain, Italy's
spine.
The US fifth was on the Mediterranean
[music]
side of Italy, driving towards Bologna.
The British began their advance at the
end of August.
The US offensive began on September
12th.
Within 10 days, the Americans had
penetrated [music] the Gothic line, but
the weather and the terrain made
progress painful.
By late October, still in the mountains
and short of Bologna, Clark [music] was
forced to close down his offensive.
He had suffered almost 16,000
casualties, [music]
losses greater than the replacement
rate.
I asked this kid in Pisa what that big
hole was and it was all wood there. He
says the Germans would get all these old
people
and they would throw them in there and
they would burn them. That's what the
the kid told me. You know, I said, "What
a terrible thing." You know,
>> the British [music] closed down their
Italian offensive at the end of
December. They had crossed the river
Conquer, the Marchio, the Rubicon, the
Savvio, the Ronco, the river Lemon, and
still faced several [music] river
obstacles before even reaching the Poe.
Italy is a difficult [music] place to
fight a war.
Although victory in Italy had not come
in 1944, significant German forces had
been tied up.
These were forces that could have made a
difference to Germany's efforts on the
second front or on the Eastern front.
But Germany was an empire suffering from
what [music] historian Paul Kennedy
termed imperial overstretch.
It had to fiercely defend gains in east
and west.
Using the shrinking resources [music] of
an embattled domestic base,
Germany's ally in Asia reacted to the
same peril [music] by going on the
attack.
Japan launched a massive offensive in
China. Operation Ichigo, operation
number one.
510,000
Japanese military personnel, a force
vastly greater than Japanese land forces
in any other theater,
embarked on an offensive with two
ambitions.
to open a land [music] and therefore
supply route to Indochina and to capture
the air bases [music] from which
American bombers were launching attacks
on the Japanese home islands and [music]
on shipping.
Marching songs were a part of Japanese
military culture.
For the Ishigo offensive, a [music] new
song was written and learned. And as
they marched, the Japanese sang.
Taking care of trees and grass, the
Japanese troops marched through Hunan
Province.
How kind their hearts are.
Our enemies are Anglo Americans.
White-faced [music]
demons.
These pictures of the evacuation of
Quailin might equally well be any one of
a thousand other places in war ravaged
China. Almost the only transport was the
single track railway and Qualin station
was soon packed with about 20,000
wouldbe passengers.
The offensive achieved its aims of
reaching Indo-China and of eliminating
bases from which US aircraft could
operate.
The kindhearted Japanese inflicted about
300,000 casualties on the Chinese,
taking 100,000 casualties themselves.
But it was all to precious little
purpose.
Events elsewhere were moving inexurably
against the Japanese whose empire was
being squeezed in the Pacific.
American bombers resumed their offensive
against Japan from bases in the newly
captured Marianas.
As Ichigo was driving into China, the
Americans were starting their campaign
to recover the Philippines.
Softening up air attacks began in
mid-occtober.
And on the 14th, the invasion force
sailed.
MacArthur's fleet comprised 420
transports [music] and 157 warships
manned by 50,000 sailors and
transporting [music] 165,000 troops.
The first landing by US Rangers occurred
on October the 17th.
On October the 20th, the main landing
went in on a 25 km front.
A substantial beach [music] head was
established with 100,000 men landed in
the first assault at a cost of 49
American dead.
Famously, MacArthur to keep the promise
he had made in 1942 had returned.
It was indeed a great moment for the
general going ashore with his men.
famously to publicize his return,
MacArthur waited [music] ashore for the
news reel cameras and to the
inconvenience of his retinue.
>> Incidentally, it's reported that shortly
after this picture was taken, bullets
from a jab plane missed him by inches.
The Imperial Army responded to the
invasion by joining air and naval power
to the defense. It shipped in
reinforcements and it bombed American
troops.
But American air superiority countered
one threat and in the greatest naval
action in history,
American naval strength decisively
defeated the other.
The second battle of the Philippine Sea
lasted from the 23rd to the 26th of
October. It was the last naval battle
between battleships.
There were moves and false moves as
naval forces divided between islands
were lost to sight in narrow channels,
turned to counter [music] landing forces
on the one hand
or carrier groups on the other.
American losses were significant.
But for Japan,
the damage was simply terminal.
80% of the vessels that Japan dispatched
to Lee Gulf had been sunk.
The Japanese fleet now had no carriers
at all.
With the fight for Lee over, the fight
for the Philippines was effectively
decided.
Although the Japanese still had 250,000
troops on Luzon, they had lost more than
50% of their air strength,
26 major warships,
60,000 men killed, and a further 10,000
drowned when their transports were sunk.
You
>> [music]
>> Victory was getting closer in the
Pacific.
In Europe, it [music] was within reach.
4 days after the Normandy landings, the
Red Army had resumed the Winter War,
intending to drive Finland and Axis
partner, out of the conflict.
The 21st Army of the Leningrad front
began the attack.
The Curelian front joined the offensive
10 days later.
On both fronts, the Fins, armed by the
Germans and supported by one German
division, were driven back.
Then the day after the Caribbean front
had moved.
>> Operation Bration opened.
[music]
It was June the 22nd, the 3rd
anniversary of the German invasion of
Russia. The Soviets had lined up [music]
300 guns per kilometer on a 560 km front
from Smolinsk through to Minsk in
Bellarussia.
11 Soviet fronts began their surge and
they surged irresistibly for 10 weeks.
The first Baltic front, General Bramian
and the third Bellarussian front,
Chernyakovski opened the Vitans Cora
offensive.
Foreign
speech. Foreign speech. Foreign speech.
by the 27th. Viteps had fallen and a
complete German army corps. The Third
Pansa army was lost.
On the 24th, Roasovski's first
Bellarussian front joined the attack. It
would swing up towards Minsk.
Churnyakovski swinging down to beat him.
Second fellow Russian front General
Zakarov crossed the river Dunipa aiming
directly for Minsk.
Third fellow Russian front reached and
crossed the river Berina the next day.
Army Group Cent's 37 divisions were
pulverized [music]
by [music] 166 Soviet divisions
supported by [music] 2,700 tanks and
1,300 assault guns.
In 2 weeks, Operation Bration had
[music] penetrated 160 km on a 400 km
front.
Seven of Army Group Cent's generals had
been killed in action.
Second Bellar Russian front. The Mogil
offensive continued its advance forcing
opposing troops back on the Berina where
they would be trapped.
Foreign
speech. Foreign speech. Foreign speech.
The third part of the initial offensive,
the Bobriusk offensive went for the
German 9inth Army on the southern flank
of Army Group Center.
Roasovvski's forces broke through the
supposedly impossible Crypet marshes,
his engineers having crossed them with
wooden causeways.
By June 27th, he had encircled two
German core east of Bobio, which was
liberated on June 29th.
For the duration of the operation,
German casualties in the east
outstripped those being taken in the
west by 4 to one.
90% of all Germans killed [music] in
combat died on the Eastern Front more
between July 1944 and May 1945 than in
the preceding 5 years.
The Minsk offensive pressed on.
Fifth Panser division was rushed forward
to plug approaches to the city. But on
July the 3rd, the second guard's tanks
core of the Red Army broke into the
city.
By the end of the fourth, the city had
fallen. 40,000 of its encircled 105,000
troops were dead and army group center
had been destroyed. In less than two
weeks, the Vey marked had lost the
equivalent of 25 divisions.
The way to Poland and to Lithuania was
open.
Forebody.
By July the 11th, Germany had lost 28
divisions. More than 30 generals had
been killed or captured. and the Red
Army had advanced 650 kilometers.
Roasovski's forces reached the river
book, the original Polish border. They
reached the eastern banks of the Vistula
on the 25th and turned to threaten
Warsaw.
On August the 1st, the Polish home army
in occupied Warsaw rose to link with the
oncoming Russians and expel the Germans
from their city and their country.
But the Russians did not come on.
They ignored the Polish uprising.
Churchill, without Soviet or American
approval, sent the RAF on more than 200
supply drops.
Hitler commanded Himmler to deal with
the Poles. 200,000 citizens and 10,000
partisan fighters were killed.
On August 20th, Russian forces entered
Romania where King Michael had his
pro-German prime minister, Yon Antlescu,
arrested. He was later executed by
firing squad.
To judge by the pictures, you'd think
Romania had always been fighting on the
side of the Allies and that the country
was now celebrating its liberation. None
of us, however, can really blame the
people of Bucharest for being delighted
to see the Germans go out and the
Russians come in.
>> [music]
>> In a reprise [music] of the Stalingrad
humiliation, German prisoners from Minsk
were marched through Moscow, 20 breast
and marched briskly. It took the parade
90 minutes to pass.
And after the parade had passed
theatrically, the streets were
disinfected.
The climax of Operation Bration
coincided with the breakout from
Normandy.
180,000 had come ashore on D-Day. by any
measure, a successful amphibious
operation, but only the beginning of an
invasion.
By the end of the first day, the Allied
position all along the line was shy of
its targets.
>> [music]
>> The most talked about stumbling block in
the first days and weeks was the city of
K.
Planning had it in Allied hands by the
end of D-Day.
It finally fell 6 weeks later and
arguments and fingerpointing continue.
But there can be no argument that a most
influential factor in the delay was the
sternness of the defense.
The third Canadian [music]
division assaulted can on D-Day + 1,
June the 7th, and was repelled by a
German division that launched numerous
fanatical counterattacks.
It was for those German defenders their
first day under fire.
The 20,000 troops had never been in
action before.
They were the 12th SS Panser Division,
Hitler Yugand,
Hitler Youth.
These soldiers had been seven when
Hitler took power. They were products of
an educational system that had been an
early and important priority of the
Third Reich.
Baldor of von Shiraak appointed to head
the Hitler Youth wrote special prayers
which these young soldiers had in
fervently.
Adolf Hitler, they prayed, you are our
great fur.
Thy name makes the enemy tremble. Thy
will alone is law upon the earth.
Let us hear daily thy voice. Order us by
thy leadership.
For we will obey to the end. And even
with our lives, we praise thee. Hail
Hitler.
By the end of the campaign, the Hitler
Youth Division would have suffered 42%
casualties.
[music]
The quality of the opposition was one
reason for the delays at Can.
Another was the problem of the boage.
[music] Sun sunken country lanes hemmed
in by tall hedros. its difficulties, for
all of the detailed planning that went
into Operation Overlord seemed to have
escaped everyone's attention.
But the Allies were steadily building
superiority in numbers of men and all
arms.
Omaha and Utah beaches had linked up by
June 12th, and the Americans turned to
cut across the Cotton Peninsula.
General Friedrich Dolman commanding the
seventh army which was facing the brunt
of the invasion
said that his troops on the cotton tan
were stretched like a bow at breaking
point.
On June the 18th, the US 7th core
reached Barnavville, cutting the
Kotantan.
The great objective now at the tip of
the Kotant was the port of Sherborg.
[music]
It fell to a sustained American assault
on June 27th,
but the dockyard installations had been
destroyed and it would be some weeks
before the port could be used for
supply.
It was now [music] second SS Panser core
recently deployed that turned back a
renewed [music] British attempt at can
the corn battle
one of the biggest tank battle in
Normandy. I was sitting on the top of my
tank and an air burst shell went off
above my head and a bit of shrapnel came
down literally between my legs and hit
the gunner down below in the turret and
killed him. Uh so I I was only about 6
in away from being killed.
The first United States Army began its
push towards Salo at the start of July
when Hitler made his last public speech.
Hardly any applause, noted Albert Spear.
>> The difficulty was that the Germans
didn't have all that number of tanks,
but they did have much better tanks than
we had. Particularly the Panther and the
Tiger, of course, there were very few
Tigers, fortunately.
They were impenetrable to us.
With a tiger around, you just really had
to avoid it. It was no good trying to
knock [music] it out. Impossible.
We had a very sharp battle
in during which we lost all the tanks.
If you're a commander and your own tank
get damaged, you swap and go into
another tank and carry on there. So, I
swapped about three times.
For some reason, they thought that was
worth giving me a medal.
RAF Bomber Command hit KN in earnest and
Operation Charmwood gained some ground
but failed to take the town.
Montgomery ordered operations to move
[music] east of K, taking the pressure
off the advancing Bradley. Following
more heavy bombing, the Canadians
finally took can
at the same time. The Americans were in
sandlow.
As the battle sweeps southward, every
one of us will agree wholeheartedly with
General Montgomery when he says,
>> "And so to every Allied soldier in
Normandy, I say, well done. Well done
indeed."
The Allies, now balanced in strength and
coordinating their actions, began to
press [music] east and towards the
breakout.
They had landed 1,450,000
men and more than 4,000 tanks.
On the 25th of July, Operation Cobra was
launched. Charwood had advanced the line
south of the beaches. Cobra, the US 7th
Corps in the Vanguard, broke the German
line.
By the end of July, Avanch had fallen.
Operation [music] Blue Coat alongside
Cobra and thrusting towards Via helped
straighten the line.
"This thing has busted wide open," said
General Leland Hobbes, commanding the US
30th Infantry Division. By the end of
July, the advance was still short of the
target, but the invader was ascendant
everywhere.
Late July, German forces had been
reduced by 113,000 men and 2,117
tanks. 10,000 men and 17 tanks had been
sent to replace them. At the end of
August, the Allies took a significant
step. The invasion force broke out of
Normandy and began the liberation of
France.
The month of August of 1944, I was with
General Patton.
We wore ties.
We're all saying, "Well, if we die, at
least we look nice."
Patton's Third Army was activated at the
beginning of August.
Its offensive into Britany followed four
lines of advance towards the significant
naval base at Breast, the port at
Laurian, the city of Ren, and south to
the river L and N.
We were going along the Britany coast
and liberating all these little towns.
We got the one town and there's this guy
shooting the church steeple at us.
So I pull the thing back for a 50
caliber.
Don't work.
Oh [__]
So I jumped over and get on a jeep.
That's most most telling experience that
[music] I had. most scary.
>> By the sixth, Laurian had been reached,
but the city, which Hitler had
designated as one of his fortresses,
would hold out until the end of the war.
On the 7th, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Ike,
the Allied Supreme Commander,
established his command post in
Normandy.
By August 25th, Patton's third army was
less than 100 kilometers from the German
border.
And yet, nine months of fierce fighting
lay ahead on both the western and the
eastern fronts
before the Third Reich collapsed in
flames.
On the 8th of August,
the Germans had launched a counterattack
which created a salient that became
known as the file pocket.
On the night of the 7th 8th, the
Canadian first army launched operation
totalize
aimed at closing the file pocket and
cutting off the German 7th army.
foreign.
[music]
I need
the fierce resistance to totalize
included the tenacious 12th SS Pansa
Hitler Youth Division.
Valz did not fall until the 16th, the
day after Operation Dragoon, the Allied
landing in the south of France.
Polar
only.
Sure.
The resolute [music] action of the Pansa
Hitler Youth Division in holding open
the neck of the pocket
allowed the escape of 300,000 soldiers
and 25,000 of their vehicles.
Hitler said that August the 18th was the
worst day of my life.
On August the 19th, the French forces of
the interior,
an alliance of resistance groups rose in
Paris.
The US 79th division crossed the Sen
and [music] Polish and American forces
linked up at Mo or Mill.
On the 21st, the File's pocket was
finally closed.
50,000 Germans were taken prisoner.
If you want to see
[music]
the cigar
Yeah.
The allies wheeling east crossed the sen
and Hitler ordered General Dietri Von
Kolitz, governor of the city to raise
Paris to the ground.
[music]
"The city must not fall into the enemy's
hand," Hitler said, "except lying in
complete rubble."
Fonolitz, who had taken up his position
only two weeks earlier, chose instead to
negotiate a ceasefire with the French,
who outnumbered his 17,000man garrison.
On August 23rd, Von Kolitz surrendered
Paris.
Two days later, Sha de Gaulle walked
triumphantly down the Shamziliz.
Flags flew. Everyone cheered.
Although some unfortunate women had
their heads shaved, no one, it seemed,
had been in the paramilitary militia.
The milis Franc says responsible for the
deaths of many resistance fighters and
the [music] deportation of the French
Jews.
No one else had collaborated.
In September, as the allies first
[music] set foot on German soil,
Churchill and a by now very ill
Roosevelt [music] met for the second
Quebec conference.
It was the [music] prime minister's wife
who told the world why they were
meeting.
>> The British people have gone through
grim times. They know now that they are
climbing to the top of the hill. [music]
But with all the just pride they feel in
the great victories in Europe,
they never forget the score they have to
settle with Japan.
That is the meaning of this Quebec
conference.
Churchill traveled from Quebec to Moscow
for talks with Stalin. What he and
Roosevelt wanted was an undertaking from
the Soviet leader that as soon as Hitler
was defeated, the Red Army would be
turned against Japan.
Stalin agreed to go to war with Japan
within two weeks of the end of the war
in Europe. And in a notorious [music]
episode, Churchill sought to sweeten the
dictator and sort out the postwar world
by scribbling what he himself called a
naughty document which proposed
percentile distribution of influence in
Europe.
Churchill passed the note to Stalin and
after a little finessing both men
signed.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Come on.